Guide to the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection, 1955-2003 SC.1976.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection
1955-2003
1970-1995
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Family Communications, Inc.
SC.1976.05
12 Linear Feet (27 boxes)
This collection contains materials related to the popular children's television show Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, which was created by Fred Rogers and aired from 1968 to 2001. This collection does not focus on the personal life of Fred Rogers; rather, it focuses on Rogers' life work to promote the well-being of children through the show, as well as Rogers' other projects. A bulk of material in this collection concerns the producing and promoting of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood during the 1970 to 1990 period. These materials include publicity photographs, press kits, scripts, and episode summaries and records.
Biography
Fred Rogers (1928-2003) was an American television personality and host of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood. He was born March 20, 1928 in Latrobe, Pa., and graduated from Latrobe High School in 1946. He studied at Dartmouth College from 1946-1948 until he transferred to Rollins College in Winter Park, Fl., where he earned his BA in music in 1951 (he wrote over 200 songs for Mister Rogers' Neighborhood). At Rollins College he met his wife, Sarah Joanne Byrd, a pianist. They married in 1952 and had two sons: James in 1959 and John in 1961. During the early 1950's he worked in New York City for NBC's musical programs,Your Hit Parade,The Kate Smith Hour, and The Voice of Firestone. After leaving NBC, he moved to Pittsburgh and worked as a puppeteer for the Pittsburgh public television station (WQED) children's show,The Children's Corner, hosted by Josie Carey. During his seven years with the program, he developed puppets (many of which he also voice acted), characters, and music — including King Friday XIII and X the Owl. While working on The Children's Corner, he studied theology at the Pittsburgh Theological Seminary and in 1963 was ordained a minister of the United Presbyterian Church. At his ordination, the Presbyterian Church asked him to serve children and families through television.
In 1963, the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC) asked Rogers to develop the program, Mister Rogers. Rogers moved to Toronto where the show ran for three seasons. In 1966, he received the rights to the program and moved the show to WQED in Pittsburgh. On February 19, 1968, distribution of the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood began and in 1970 the show moved to PBS. In 1971, Rogers formed the non-profit production company Family Communications Inc. (now known as Fred Rogers Productions).
Mister Rogers' Neighborhood ran for 895 episodes, from 1968-2001. In 1997 he accepted the Lifetime Achievement Award at the 24th Annual Daytime Emmy Awards. Rogers was diagnosed with stomach cancer in 2002 and passed away the following year. His wife, Joanne Rogers, a professional duo-concert pianist and dedicated philanthropist, continues to live in Pittsburgh where she works to preserve his legacy.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains materials related to the popular children's television show Mister Rogers' Neighborhood (which is referred to as MRN throughout the finding aid), which was created by Fred Rogers and aired from 1968 to 2001. This collection does not focus on the personal life of Fred Rogers; rather, it focuses on Rogers' life work to promote the well-being of children through the show MRN, as well as Rogers' other projects. Ways that Fred Rogers performed this work outside of the Neighborhood included producing non-MRN television programs, writing articles about children, giving speeches, and creating materials for parents and daycare providers to utilize. Some of the materials in this collection were produced by Family Communications, Inc., Fred Rogers' production group.
The bulk of material in this collection concerns the producing and promoting of MRN during the 1970 to 1990 period. These materials include publicity photographs, press kits, scripts, and episode summaries and records. This collection also contains materials that analyze the impact and cultural value of MRN. There are few original documents written by Rogers himself. Other highlights of this collection include fan mail, photographs which viewers sent in to Rogers, a script from the special about the Kennedy assassination, and Yo-Yo Ma and Jeanne Marie Laskas' contributions to a University of Pittsburgh Press book about MRN.
Please note that we do not have access to A/V materials. Episodes of MRN can be purchased from Amazon.com.
The 15 MRN puppets donated with this collection are on permanent loan to the Children's Museum of Pittsburgh. Those puppets are: Ana Platypus, Cornflake S. Pecially, Daniel Striped Tiger, Dr. Bill Platypus, Edgar Cooke, Elsie Jean Platypus, Grandpere, Harriet Elizabeth Cow, Henrietta Pussycat, King Friday XIII, Lady Elaine Fairchilde, Prince Tuesday (adolescent), Prince Tuesday (baby), Queen Sara Saturday, and X the Owl.
Related Material
The Fred Rogers Center at St. Vincent College holds original, handwritten texts by Fred Rogers including letters to personal friends and professional colleagues; ideas and outlines from his earliest children's television program (The Children's Corner with Josie Carey); scripts and production books from Mister Rogers' Neighborhood; public service announcements for both children and adults; and speeches. The Fred Rogers Center at St. Vincent Collection is the primary repository holding materials about or by Fred Rogers; the collection at the University of Pittsburgh contains copies of select materials held at St. Vincent. They can be reached at info@fredrogerscenter.org or at 724-805-2750.
Margaret Kimmel Records on Fred Rogers, 1973-2003, SC.1990.05, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Don Brockett Papers, 1930-1995, CTC.2002.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Margaret Hodges Papers, 1911-2006, SC.1990.03, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Joe Negri Collection, 1930-2014, CAM.JNC.2014, Center for American Music, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
The Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection was gifted by Family Communications, Inc. to the University of Pittsburgh School of Library & Information Sciences on January 17, 1989.
Arrangement
The original order (according to how it was received from the Information Sciences Library) has mostly been retained. In some cases, folders were moved from one series to another and folder titles have been amended to better reflect folder contents.
Series I. Background
Series II. Speeches
Series III. Articles
Series IV. Correspondence
Series V. Radio and Television News Coverage
Series VI. Photographs
Series VII. Promotional Materials
Series VIII. Production Materials
Series IX. Materials for Children
Series X. University of Pittsburgh Book
Series XI. Research
Series XII. Non-MRN Programs
Series XIII. Newspaper Articles and Clippings
Series XIV. Oversize
Custodial History
The Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection was gifted by Family Communications, Inc. to the University of Pittsburgh School of Library & Information Sciences and housed in the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room on January 17, 1989. When the Information Sciences Library closed in August 2012, the collections housed in the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room, including the Mister Rogers' Neighborhood Collection, were incorporated into the Archives & Special Collections Department, University Library System.
Access Restrictions
The materials in Series IV. Correspondence have restricted access. Researchers must agree to accept the terms and sign a confidentiality agreement provided by the Archives & Special Collections Department in order to consult this material. All other portions of the collection have no restrictions.
Television producers and directors -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Puppets; Children's television programs; Rogers, Fred -- Performances; Mister Rogers' neighborhood (Television program); Public Broadcasting Service (U.S.); Family Communications, Inc.; WQED (Television station: Pittsburgh, Pa.); Rogers, Mister (Fred); Mister Rogers' neighborhood (Television program); Fred Rogers Company
- Background, 1955-2003; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents that give an overview of who Fred Rogers was, and what his show Mister Rogers' Neighborhood was all about. Most of the documents in this series are publicity documents or press releases created by Family Communications and intended for distribution among the public press. There are a few photocopies of sections of books that contained relevant biographical/background information. Folder 4 contains a few invitations and programs as well as a list of awards received.
  - Biographies of Fred Rogers, 1971-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biography of David Newell (Mr. McFeely), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Information about Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards, recognition, and tributes, 1955-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Speeches, 1969-1992; 1972-1980; II.
  This series contains the speech texts of speeches given by, about, and to Fred Rogers. The speech texts encompass a broad range of events, from conferences, symposiums, and senate hearings to commencement speeches and other events that took place at academic institutions.
  - By Fred Rogers, 1969-1992; 1972-1980; 1.
    This subseries contains the text for speeches given by Fred Rogers. Notable speech texts include Fred Rogers' statement at the Senate Hearings on Public Broadcasting, the National Symposium on Children and Television, and the Johnson & Johnson Symposium on the Family. Folder 5 contains a summary of speeches Fred Rogers gave from 1972 to 1980.
    - Bibliography of speeches, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Speech texts, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Speech texts, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Speech texts, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - By others, 1972-1975; 2.
    This subseries contains speeches given by Hedda Sharapan, an associate producer of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, cast member David Newell, and remarks given at a ceremony honoring Fred Rogers at the University of Pittsburgh.
    - Speech texts by MRN staff, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Speech texts at the University of Pittsburgh, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Articles, 1968-2002; III.
  This series contains articles written by Fred Rogers himself, not articles written about Fred Rogers by others. The articles are the finished versions that were published in magazines or newspapers; this series does not contain drafts for the articles. Many of the original magazines and newspaper clippings are present, though some are photocopies of the originals. Some topics Fred Rogers touches on in his articles are child safety, back to school, children and TV, celebrating Christmas with your child, and understanding children's needs.
  - Articles, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Articles, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Articles, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1971-1992; IV.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains letters written to Fred Rogers from the viewers of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, and other correspondence.
  Access Restrictions
  The materials in Series IV. Correspondence have restricted access. Researchers must agree to accept the terms and sign a confidentiality agreement provided by the Archives & Special Collections Department in order to consult this material.
  - Viewers, 1971-1992; 1985-1992; 1.
    This subseries contains fan mail from children and adults alike written to Fred Rogers. This subseries does not contain any of his replies to their mail. Some letters are typed, and some are handwritten, but they all appear to be photocopies of the originals, except for some of the children's letters which are originals.
    - Children, 1972-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Adults, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Adults, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1989; 2.
    This subseries contains correspondence about articles and interviews with Fred Rogers, and about a donation of film footage to the University of Pittsburgh. There is also a photograph of Fred Rogers and a Mister Rogers' Neighborhood holidays greeting card.
    - Articles and interviews, 1974-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Donation of film footage, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mister Rogers' Neighborhood holidays greeting card, circa 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Radio and Television News Coverage, 1982-1990; V.
  This series has radio coverage of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood from KOMO Editorial and Burrelle's, and television coverage from Burrelle's and Luce Press Clippings. Major topics covered include the Burger King ad controversy, the donation of Fred Rogers' sweater to the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of American History, and debates on the future of and regulations for children's television programming. The "notifications" folders contain summaries of any television content that included the keyword "Mr. Rogers' Neighborhood." This content often includes parodies, jokes, references, or other instances not directly related to discussion of the actual show.
  - Radio transcripts, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Television, Burrelle's transcripts, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Television, Luce's transcripts, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Television, Luce's transcripts, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Television, Luce's notifications, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Television, Luce's notifications, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs, 1973-1994; VI.
  This series contains photographs pertaining to either Fred Rogers or Mister Rogers' Neighborhood. There are photos likely used for promotional reasons for MRN and Fred Rogers' other television projects. The contact sheets are photos actually used in the production of the show. Few photos are candid shots, with the exception of subseries 2.
  - Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, 1979-1994; 1.
    This subseries contains photos of Fred Rogers, cast members, and the puppets. There is text at the bottom of the photographs explaining the content and context of the images. The images of the cast members in this subseries are taken on the set of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood. For headshots of the cast members, see Series VII: Promotional Materials. The photos of Fred Rogers are mostly posed photographs, and include a few images of his family. Children's Corner was the television program that Fred Rogers was part of prior to creating MRN, and is considered a forerunner to MRN (some of the puppets were first introduced on the set of Children's Corner).
    - Fred Rogers, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Fred Rogers and cast members on set, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Neighborhood of Make-Believe puppets, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Children's Corner (precursor to MRN), circa 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Guests, 1979-1994
      This section contains photos of Fred Rogers with special guests, usually on the set of the show. There is usually text at the bottom of the photo that states what they are doing in the photo, what episode the guest is featured in, and any other relevant information.
      - Captain Kangaroo, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Embery, Joan, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Ferrigno, Lou, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Jenkins, Ella, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Kloss, Eric, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Lee, Stephen, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Marsalis, Wynton, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - McConnell, Suzie, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Vedeneeva, Tatiana, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photos of viewers, 1988-1989; 2.
    This subseries contains photographs that fans mailed in to Fred Rogers. Almost all are candid or school portraits of children, but there are some photos of adults, too. Many have inscriptions on the backs of the photos. The photos were originally formatted in scrapbook-like photo albums, and there are remnants of the decorations and categorization. A note states that the contents have been removed from the original scrapbook for preservation purposes. It is unclear who created the photo albums, or whether they were ever a gift to Fred Rogers. Some sections appear to be themed. It is also unclear whether the photos were solicited (send in a picture of yourself doing…) or completely voluntary. The beginning folders seem to be mostly school portraits, and the later folders appear to be themed. Original organization has tried to be preserved where indication of organization is given.
    - Album #1, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - Album #2, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Album #2, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Other projects, 1987-1992; 3.
    This subseries contains photographs from Old Friends, New Friends,Mister Rogers Talks with Parents… and Fred Rogers' visits to schoolchildren. The Miscellaneous folder includes candid photos of Fred Rogers at work.
    - Fred Rogers visits children, 1987-1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Mister Rogers Talks with Parents... TV special, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Old Friends, New Friends, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Contact sheets for Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, 1973; 4.
    This subseries contains contact sheets, which are the pieces of photographic paper onto which several or all of the negatives on a roll of film have been contact printed. Only one folder is actually dated. It's possible all of the contact sheets are circa 1973. Some of the contact sheets are marked up, and there are different image sizes on some of the contact sheets.
    - #1-10, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - #11-20 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - #21-30A (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - #31-40 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - #41-50 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - #51-60 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - #61-69 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - #72-80 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - #81-86 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - #100-118 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - #123-145 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - #146-155 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - #156-165 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - #166-175 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - #176-187 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - #1-12 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - #13-22 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - A-I (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Unknown (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Promotional Materials, 1971-2001; 1986-2001; VII.
  This series contains materials distributed mostly to television stations to aid in their publicizing of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood. The promotional binder of subseries 1 was an all-at-once bulk reference material, with the press kits of subseries 2 intended to supplement the promotional binder on a weekly or as-needed basis. There is one oversize box of materials for this series, which contains issues of the Around the Neighborhood newsletter.
  - Promotional binder, 1971; 1.
    This subseries is composed of a binder containing comprehensive and detailed bulk promotional material which was distributed to the promotion directors of the public television stations that aired Mister Rogers' Neighborhood. This binder, containing multiple chapters of carefully organized information on the show, was created as a resource for television station publicity managers in order to give them the greatest flexibility in the "mutual promotion/publicity of your station and [MRN]." Contents include:
    Chapter 1. General Information
    Chapter 2. Philosophy
    Chapter 3. Cast and Programs
    Chapter 4. Photography
    Chapter 5. Print and Utilization Materials
    Chapter 6. Publicizing Mister Rogers' Neighborhood.
    Note: the individual sheets of paper were removed from the binder and were re-housed in folders by chapter. The Miscellaneous folder contains a catalog of the MRN music albums, an image of Fred Rogers, photographic slides, and a pamphlet called You, Your Child, and Mister Rogers.
    - Introduction and Chapter 1, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 2, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 3, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 4, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 5, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 6, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Press kits, 1986-2001; 2.
    This subseries contains folders created by Family Communications to be distributed to the press, encouraging the recipients to publicize Mister Rogers' Neighborhood. Content was prepared by Family Communications to make it easy for the press to use. The press kits were created by the Public Relations directors of MRN/Family Communications and were given to the Public Information Directors and Program Managers of the PBS television station or other TV stations that aired MRN.
    - Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, 1997
      This section contains information for the press about the show in general, which takes the form of letters, press releases, memos, and a newsletter. This includes material on the philosophy of the show, but does not detail specific episodes. Most of the material concerns the 30th anniversary of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, with information on special events like community service projects, workshops and trainings, and honors that Fred Rogers received that year.
      - General, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - 30 Years on PBS (8197) and TV Guide Honor, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Programs, 1986-2001
      This section contains folders for the upcoming theme week of Mister Rogers' Neighborhood that may include press releases, photographs, spot copy, program notes, program listings, possible content for program guides, the Around the Neighborhood newsletter, and other publicity information. Usually addressed to the Public Information Directors.
      - Episodes 1561-1565: Celebrations, May 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Episodes 1461-1465: Mister Rogers Goes to School, August 1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Episodes 1566-1570: Playthings, November 1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Episodes 1571-1575: Dancing, March 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Episodes 1576-1580: Making Mistakes, May 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Episodes 1461-1465: Mister Rogers Goes to School, August 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Episodes 1581-1585: Alike and Different, November 1987 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Episodes 1585-1590: Nighttime, March 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Episodes 1591-1595: Kindness, May 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Episodes 1461-1465: Mister Rogers Goes to School, August 1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Episodes 1596-1600: Secrets, November 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Episodes 1601-1605: Fun and Games, February 1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Episodes 1606-1610: Josephine the Short-Neck Giraffe, May 1989 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Episodes 1611-1615: When Parents go to Work, November 1989 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Episodes 1616-1620: The Environment, April 1990 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Episodes 1621-1625: Fathers and Music, July-August 1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Episodes 1626-1630: Mouths and Feelings, November 1990 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Episodes 1631-1635: Growing, February 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Episodes 1636-1640: Dress-up, August 1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Episodes 1641-1645: Art, November 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Episodes 1646-1650: Imaginary Friends, February 1992 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Episodes 1656-1660: Up and Down, November 1992 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Episodes 1661-1665: Love, February 1993 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Episodes 1671-1675: Things to Wear, February 1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Episodes 1681-1685: Fast and Slow, February 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Episodes 1461-1465: Mister Rogers Goes to School, August 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Episodes 1691-1695: What Do You Do with the Mad That You Feel, March 1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)